Finding Aid for Law Library (University of Michigan) Records 1859-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Collections
  - Collections, 1902-1954
    - Facts Relating to Legal Education in the United States compiled for the use of the Committee of the Faculty of the Law Department of the University of Michigan, 1907; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Horace Wilgus Letters, 1922-1925 (Box 18)
    - Institute on Changes Caused by Internal Revenue Code, 1954 (Box 18)
    - Institute on Creditors Remedies, 1954 (Box 18)
    - Institute on the New Business Receipts Tax, 1953 (Box 18)
    - James Campbell Lectures on Shipping and Admiralty, Photostats and transcripts, 6 folders (Box 18)
    - Lectures on Insurance by Melville Bigelow, 1902 (Box 18)
    - Lectures on Public International Law by James B. Angell, circa 1902 (Box 18)
    - Richard E. Stifle Photo Album of Law Faculty, 1947 (Box 18)
      (Ralph Aigler, Kenneth Cox, Grover Grismore, Paul Kauper, Albert Neumann, George Palmer, Burke Shartel, Lewis Simes, Russell Smith)
    - Richard Stifle photos? (Box 18)
      (loose photos similar to album content)
    - Thomas Bogle Memorial, 1921 (Box 18)
    - Victor Lane Memorial, 1930 (Box 18)
    - William Cook document introducing John B. Trevor, 1927 (Box 18)
- Audio Visual Material
  The Audio Visual series includes photographs, slides, cassette tapes, and audio reels. The photograph section includes those taken of the construction of the new building on January 10, 1980 and outsize mounted photographs taken by Balthazar Korab of proposed models of the new building. The slides consist of around 250 slides of alternative schemes for the law school additions, and details of the law school, proposed library additions, and the built addition.
  In 1990, sound recordings of the Thomas M. Cooley, William W. Bishop, and William W. Cook Lectures were added to the Law Library's records. Additional records of these lectures, including correspondence pertaining to arrangements along with programs and printed copies of the presentation may be found in the University of Michigan Law School records also held by the Bentley.
  A second set of audio-visual material was added to the collection in 2014. This includes glass plate slides of the library and the law school buildings, and negatives of individuals collected from a number of sources, among them secondary sources. Cassette tapes are also included which have the recordings of various lectures, including from the Cook and Cooley lecture series' and from lectures given by James White. Also included are audio reel-to-reel tapes that contain recordings of presentations at conferences, including the Institute on Advocacy and the Institute on Improving the Method of Judicial Selection in Michigan.
  - Photographs
    - New Building Photographs, January 10, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Korab photos, 5 prints (Folder 1)
    - Floor plans (Box 20)
    - Identified Individual Negatives of alumni and others (in envelopes) (Box 20)
    - Reading Room (Box 20)
  - Slides
    - Alternative Schemes for Law School Additions (Box 10)
    - Details of Law School, Proposed Library Additions, and Built Addition (Box 10)
    - Law Buildings, 2 boxes (Box 20)
    - Law Library, 2 boxes (Box 20)
  - Sound Recordings
    - Thomas M. Cooley Lectures
      - Thomas Cooley Lecture Programs, Summary of Lectures Norval Morris, "The Future of Imprisonment", 1974; 7-in. reel (Box 10)
      - Calabresi, Guido -- Nonsense on Stilts, 1979; 4 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - Bell, Daniel, 1980; 2 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - Howe, Irving, 1984; 3 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - Slote, Henrietta, 1981; 3 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - Harold Leventhal, "Science in the Courts", 1978; 7-in. reel (Box 10)
      - Melvin A. Eisenberg, "The Theory of Adjudication", 1985; 3 audiocassettes (Box 10)
      - R. Kent Greenawalt, "Religious Convictions and Lawmaking", 1986; 3 audiocassettes (Box 10)
      - Anthony T. Kronman, "Politics, Character, and the Profession of Law", 1987 (Box 10)
      - Louis Henkin, "Constitutionalism, Democracy and Foreign Affairs", 1988; 3 audiocassettes (Box 10)
    - William W. Bishop Lectures
      - Francis Jacobs, "Constitutional Developments in the European Community and the Impact of the Single Market after 1992", 1989 (Box 10)
    - William W. Cook Lectures
      - David Brion Davis, "Exodus and African Colonization", 1988; 2 audiocassettes (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures
      - Antidumping Law: Policy and Implementation Conference, 1978; 4 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - Francis, Allen-The Decline of the Rehabilitative Ideal: Penal Policy and Public Purpose, 1979; 2 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - Henkin, Louis -- A New Restatement of the Law of American Foreign Relations, 1979; 2 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - Law Library Lectures, 1981; 8 audiocassettes (Box 21)
      - White, James -- Discussion as Role Play, 1983 (Box 21)
      - White, James -- Inaugural Lecture: Moral Conflict of Advocate's Role, 1984; 2 audiocassettes (Box 21)
    - Conferences and Institutes, 1953-1955
      - Conference on Labor-Management Arbitration, 1954; 5 reels (Box 21)
      - Institute on Advocacy 5th, 1954; 6 reels (Box 21)
      - Institute on Advocacy 6th, 1955; 13 reels (Box 21)
      - Institute on Improving the Method of Judicial Selection in Michigan, 1954; 3 reels (Box 21)
      - Institute on New Michigan Business Receipts Tax, 1953; 3 reels (Box 21)
- William Cook Papers
  The William Cook Papers series is primarily related to Cook's book American Institutions and Their Preservation. This is divided into its own subseries and contains correspondence, notes, memos, and early drafts of the document. At the end of the series is a file entitled "The Composite American and His Mission," which was the early title of this book. The series also contains other articles, correspondence, miscellaneous writings, and memos.
  - American Institutions and Their Preservation
    - 1st Edition, Letters and Reviews, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Corrections, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1925-1927; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Extracts from Census Reports and World Almanacs, 1924-1925 (Box 11)
    - Index to Authors (Box 11)
    - Memos, 1929-1930 (Box 11)
    - New Manuscript for 3rd Edition, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Quotations, 8 folders (Box 11)
    - Quotations, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Research Articles, 1926-1927 (Box 12)
    - Sheets Subsequent to Completion of 1st Edition, 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Articles and Memos, 1922-1923 (Box 12)
  - Article -- "Power and Responsibility of the American Bar", 1925 (Box 12)
  - Cook Bequests-Martha Cook/Lawyer's Club, 1922-1924 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence
    - Article on Legal Research, 1927 (Box 12)
    - "Cook on Telegraph Law", 1930 (Box 12)
    - Legal Research, 1927 (Box 12)
  - Memos, 1927 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1922-1923 (Box 12)
  - Publications, 1921-1929; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - "The Composite American and His Mission" Newspaper Clippings, 1925-1926 (Box 12)
- Law School, 1901-1993
  The Law School series contains documents that were donated to the Law Library but were related to the Law School rather than a particular aspect of the library. This includes announcements, flyers, directories, scrapbooks (located in outsize material), and two subseries. The Michigan Law Review subseries includes chronological issues, lists of authors, and meeting minutes. The second subseries contains information on the Lawyer's Club, a group of students within the Law School that is centered around the exclusive housing within the Law Quadrangle. The Lawyer's Club's files contain documentation including blueprints for the building, publications, rules of housing, and a series of student notebooks from alumnus Allan Rubin.
  - Law 752, 1991-1993 (Box 18)
  - Lawyer's Club
    - Billet (Box 18)
    - Board of Directors, 1936-1937 (Box 18)
    - Construction (Specifications Bathroom Section A), 1933 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1979 (Box 18)
    - History ("The Drama in the Evolution of the Lawyers Club and the Michigan Law Quadrangle" by Olga M. Overn and The Story of William W. Cook's Gift), circa 1959 (Box 18)
    - Residence and contracts, 1939-1967 (Box 18)
    - Signed Book of Names (Bimu C430) (Folder 1)
  - Lily Roberts' Ford Foundation European Trip, 1965 (Box 18)
  - Michigan Law Review (Box 19)
    - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1947-1958 (Box 19)
    - Articles of Association, 1918-1947 (Box 19)
    - Association By-laws, 1947-1965 (Box 19)
    - Authors of Student Material and Index to Student Writers, 1964-1985; 8 folders (Box 19)
    - Board of Directors Minutes, 1935-1967 (Box 19)
    - Editorial Board and Faculty Advisory Board Meetings, 1965-1989
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2089 removed to vault storage]
    - Faculty Advisory Board and Background, 1963-1965 (Box 19)
    - Financial Records
      - Bills, 1902-1903 (Box 19)
      - Statements, 1919-1932; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - History File and Correspondence, 1901-1952 (Box 19)
    - Orientation Material, 1989 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook of Newspaper Articles about Law School, 1940s (Box 22)
- (Outsize Material listed previously)
  - Law School Expansion Final Report, Venturi, Scott Brown and Associates, May 2000 (Box 22)